<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: ci | Stewart Gleadow's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://sgleadow.github.com/blog/categories/ci/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://sgleadow.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-03-01T19:52:28+11:00</updated>
  <id>http://sgleadow.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Stewart Gleadow]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Enabling Accessibility Programatically on iOS Devices]]></title>
    <link href="http://sgleadow.github.com/blog/2011/11/16/enabling-accessibility-programatically-on-ios-devices/"/>
    <updated>2011-11-16T08:29:00+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://sgleadow.github.com/blog/2011/11/16/enabling-accessibility-programatically-on-ios-devices</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I wrote a recent post on <a href="/blog/2011/10/14/enabling-accessibility-for-ios-applications/">enabling accessibility for iOS applications</a>, which ended with a snippet of code for automatically enabling accessibility on the iOS simulator. This is essential if you want to have your tests running on a continuous integration server, since the accessibility inspector is off by default.</p>

<p>I hadn't yet found a solution for enabling accessibility on the device. We need accessibility turned on so that we can access the UIAccessibility values that we use in automated functional tests in one of the <a href="/blog/2011/10/26/which-automated-ios-testing-tool-to-use/">common automated testing tools</a>. My solution up until now has been to turn VoiceOver on, which is a real pain. Since I sometimes use screenshot-based regression tests, VoiceOver breaks the tests since it visually highlights the selected item.</p>

<p><a href="http://twitter.com/#!/0xced">Cedric Luthi</a> commented on my previous post that it may be possible to modify his code to also enable accessibility on the device. I wasn't sure how that would work with the app sandbox, and whether it was an application or system preference setting. Last night I gave it a try, and amazingly it worked.</p>

<p>I wrote a simple application based on the master-detail iPhone template in Xcode 4, and wrote a quick <a href="https://github.com/square/KIF">KIF</a> test that checked a label on the master screen, pushed through to the detail screen and checked a label there also. It's a gimmick test, but enough that it will fail if accessibility is <em>not</em> enabled because none of the labels will be available to the test.</p>

<p>After following the standard KIF set up instructions, I write the following test:</p>

<p>```objc
- (void)initializeScenarios;
{</p>

<pre><code>KIFTestScenario *loadScreen = [KIFTestScenario scenarioWithDescription:@"Test app loads up on correct screen"];
[loadScreen addStep:[KIFTestStep stepToWaitForViewWithAccessibilityLabel:@"Master"]];
[self addScenario:loadScreen];


KIFTestScenario *navigateToDetails = [KIFTestScenario scenarioWithDescription:@"Test can navigate"];
[navigateToDetails addStep:[KIFTestStep stepToTapViewWithAccessibilityLabel:@"Detail"]];
[navigateToDetails addStep:[KIFTestStep stepToWaitForViewWithAccessibilityLabel:@"Detail view content goes here"]];
[self addScenario:navigateToDetails];
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<p>That works fine on the simulator, whether you have explicitly enabled accessibility or not now that the maintainers of KIF have merged in <a href="https://github.com/square/KIF/pull/78">my pull request</a>. That code only runs for the simulator, and does nothing if <code>IPHONE_SIMULATOR_ROOT</code> is not available in the <code>[[NSProcessInfo processInfo] environment]</code>. The KIF test will only run on the device (at least for me) if I turned VoiceOver on, which is a pain and not possible to automate.</p>

<p>I modified the code so that on the device, it does not try to prepend the simulator root when running on the device, and points to <code>@"/System/Library/PrivateFrameworks/AppSupport.framework/AppSupport"</code> directly. Amazingly, the KIF test then worked and all accessibility values were available to the tests. The updated code to enable accessibility programmatically on the device or the simulator looks like this:</p>

<p>```objc
+ (void)_enableAccessibilityInSimulator;
{</p>

<pre><code>NSAutoreleasePool *autoreleasePool = [[NSAutoreleasePool alloc] init];
NSString *appSupportLocation = @"/System/Library/PrivateFrameworks/AppSupport.framework/AppSupport";

NSDictionary *environment = [[NSProcessInfo processInfo] environment];
NSString *simulatorRoot = [environment objectForKey:@"IPHONE_SIMULATOR_ROOT"];
if (simulatorRoot) {
    appSupportLocation = [simulatorRoot stringByAppendingString:appSupportLocation];
}

void *appSupportLibrary = dlopen([appSupportLocation fileSystemRepresentation], RTLD_LAZY);

CFStringRef (*copySharedResourcesPreferencesDomainForDomain)(CFStringRef domain) = dlsym(appSupportLibrary, "CPCopySharedResourcesPreferencesDomainForDomain");

if (copySharedResourcesPreferencesDomainForDomain) {
    CFStringRef accessibilityDomain = copySharedResourcesPreferencesDomainForDomain(CFSTR("com.apple.Accessibility"));

    if (accessibilityDomain) {
        CFPreferencesSetValue(CFSTR("ApplicationAccessibilityEnabled"), kCFBooleanTrue, accessibilityDomain, kCFPreferencesAnyUser, kCFPreferencesAnyHost);
        CFRelease(accessibilityDomain);
    }
}

[autoreleasePool drain];
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<p>I'm a little bit unsure of the security of this, and whether you actually want your tests messing with your phones system settings on the device - but I usually have separate test devices to my personal phone, and the KIF code is never part of the actual production app that you submit to Apple, so I'm comfortable with it for now. I'm hoping this combined with my <a href="/blog/2011/11/05/installing-ios-apps-on-the-device-from-the-command-line">recent work with fruitstrap</a> could get us all the way to functional tests running on a physical device in CI.</p>

<p>You can find this code in <a href="https://github.com/sgleadow/KIF">my fork of KIF</a>, and I'm hoping after a bit of testing it can be merged into the main KIF repo, so I sent them <a href="https://github.com/square/KIF/pull/93">this pull request</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Installing iOS Apps on the Device From the Command Line]]></title>
    <link href="http://sgleadow.github.com/blog/2011/11/05/installing-ios-apps-on-the-device-from-the-command-line/"/>
    <updated>2011-11-05T10:50:00+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://sgleadow.github.com/blog/2011/11/05/installing-ios-apps-on-the-device-from-the-command-line</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One of the reasons I run most of my tests in the simulator is that it is easy to install and run applications automatically from the command line with tools like <a href="https://github.com/Fingertips/ios-sim">ios-sim</a>. Being able to run your tests from the command line make s it simple to set up continuous integration. I've used an Applescript to drive iTunes back in Xcode 3 days but it just felt wrong.</p>

<p>The most recent functional testing tool I've been playing with is Apple's own <em>UIAutomation</em>, which runs within the Instruments app. I'll write more about that separately, but let's just say I don't think it's an ideal testing tool, especially if TDD and CI are important to you. Some details are in my <a href="/blog/2011/10/30/adding-unit-tests-to-an-existing-ios-project">comparison of a few functional testing tools</a>. The <code>instruments</code> command line tool does not seem to install the app on the device before running tests, which means you still need to use Xcode to manually install the app. Enter <code>fruitstrap</code>.</p>

<h2>Fruitstrap</h2>

<p><a href="https://github.com/ghughes/fruitstrap">Fruitstrap</a> is a command line tool that uses the private MobileDevice API to install an iOS application on a physical device over USB. It's pretty easy to get set up.</p>

<p><code>
git clone git://github.com/ghughes/fruitstrap.git
cd fruitstrap
make fruitstrap
</code></p>

<p>Fruitstrap comes with a demo applicaiton, which you can compile and install on a device using <code>make install</code>. I actually had a few issues getting the demo app to work, but I did get it working for actual sample applications. You now have the <code>fruitstrap</code> command compiled and ready to go - if you want to access the command from anywhere you probably want to add it to you path, or sym link it to <code>/usr/local/bin</code> or however you like to tinker with your machine.</p>

<h2>Building from the command line</h2>

<p>I made a little sample application to play around with <code>fruitstrap</code> and scripting on my <a href="https://github.com/sgleadow">github</a>, in a project called <a href="https://github.com/sgleadow/fruitstrap-demo">fruitstrap-demo</a>. It's just a simple Single View Application with a couple of labels so you know it's the right app. To get the repository:</p>

<p><code>git clone git://github.com/sgleadow/fruitstrap-demo.git</code></p>

<p>Just to make sure everything is working, open up the project in Xcode and build and run to your device. If that doesn't work, fruitstrap isn't going to help you much. The <code>xcodebuild</code> command allows us to build our iOS apps from the command line fairly easily. The command I used was:</p>

<p><code>
xcodebuild -scheme fruitstrap-demo -sdk iphoneos build
</code></p>

<p>Remember to use the <code>iphoneos</code> so that it builds your app for the device. Note, I originally tried this with the old <em>target</em> settings for <code>xcodebuild</code>, but it turned out I needed to use schemes for reasons explained below. The app will be built to <code>build/Debug-iphoneos/fruitstrap-demo.app</code>.</p>

<h2>Try out fruitstrap</h2>

<p>Now we have an application build on the command line, let's make sure fruitstrap works for our app. Make sure to remove your sample app from the device beforehand so you know it's working. Then use the <code>xcodebuild</code> command above to compile the app so it's ready to go, and make sure you know the full path to fruitstrap, or you've put fruitstrap on your path.</p>

<p><code>
fruitstrap build/Debug-iphoneos/fruitstrap-demo.app
</code></p>

<p>You should see a bunch of output and progress information finishing with the magic <code>[100%] Installed package build/Debug-iphoneos/fruitstrap-demo.app</code>, and in a few moments, the app appears in <em>Springboard</em> on your phone. That's pretty cool - I've been trying to find a solution for installing on the device like that for a long time!</p>

<p>If you have more than one device plugged in (which is usually the case on a mobile continuous integration server), you'll need to also specify the device id.</p>

<h2>Scripting the fruitstrap installation</h2>

<p>My next goal is to write a little shell script that we can integrate into a build phase in Xcode, so that we don't have to hard code the path <code>build/Debug-iphoneos</code> into out shell script. I immediately reached for the Build Phases tab of the fruitstrap-demp target to optionally run the fruitstrap install code. However, these shell scripts seem to get called <em>before</em> the code signing is run, in which case, installing to the device will fail.</p>

<p>I found out from <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/1409981/how-to-run-a-script-after-xcode-runs-codesign-on-my-iphone-app">this stackoverflow thread</a> that you can run pre and post scripts for a scheme. This allows us to hook up a shell script to run fruitstrap <em>after</em> the code signing.</p>

<p>There is only one scheme in the sample project, so select <em>Edit Scheme...</em>, and select the <em>Build</em> action from the list on the left hand side. There are no actions at the moment, so press the <strong>+</strong> button and add a <em>Run Script Action</em>. Since we need to know where our target has been compiled, make sure that the <em>provide build settings from</em> option is set to <em>fruitstrap-demo</em>, as show in the following screenshot.</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/fruitstrap/fruitstrap-scheme-post-script.png" title="Running a script in the post action for a scheme" ></p>

<p>The actual script code is shown below. It only runs if the <code>FRUITSTRAP_CLI</code> environment variable is set, since most of the time we don't want Xcode to be using this third party tool to install on the device. We only need it to run when running from the command line as part of our continuous integration build. It seems the scheme scripts do not get run in the same working directory as you run xcodebuild, so our script makes sure to change to SRCROOT before running fruitstrap.</p>

<p>```</p>

<h1>Do nothing unless we are running from the command line</h1>

<p>if [ "$FRUITSTRAP_CLI" = "" ]; then
exit 0
fi</p>

<p>echo "<strong><strong><strong><strong><strong><strong><strong><strong><strong>"
echo "Installing app to device using fruitstrap..."
echo "Workspace location: $SRCROOT"
echo "Install location: $TARGET_BUILD_DIR/$FULL_PRODUCT_NAME"
echo "</strong></strong></strong></strong></strong></strong></strong></strong></strong>"</p>

<p>cd $SRCROOT
fruitstrap $TARGET_BUILD_DIR/$FULL_PRODUCT_NAME</p>

<p>echo "******************"
```</p>

<p>Check that when you run the xcodebuild example above that it <em>does not</em> run fruitstrap, since we don't want it to in that normal operation. Now, try building the scheme with the environment variable set and check that it does in fact build and install to the device.</p>

<p><code>
FRUITSTRAP_CLI=1 xcodebuild -scheme fruitstrap-demo -sdk iphoneos build
</code></p>

<p>Done. One command to build and install the app on the device.</p>

<h2>More about fruitstrap</h2>

<p>There is more information about fruitstrap on <a href="https://github.com/ghughes/fruitstrap">its github page</a>.</p>

<p>One extra feature fruitstrap has is to be able to launch the application and attach a debugger, by using the <code>-d</code> option. I've had mixed success with this feature, it doesn't always work for me. I'm not sure how much use it is to me anyway if the point of this is running in CI.</p>

<p><code>
fruitstrap -d build/Debug-iphoneos/fruitstrap-demo.app
</code></p>

<h2>Summary</h2>

<p>Now we can build the application and install it on the device from the command line. From here, the next step is to hook it up to the <code>instruments</code> command line interface. Massive thanks to <a href="https://twitter.com/#!/heardrwt">Richie</a> for letting me know about fruitstrap.</p>

<p>Ideally, I would like to be able to boot the app on the device <em>without</em> being hooked into the debugger. I'm not sure if this is possible, I certainly haven't got it working with fruitstrap yet - and the hairy C code isn't making me want to jump in and try just yet. What we have now is enough to get UIAutomation up and running, since <code>instruments</code> will boot the app when the tests start. However, I'd prefer to use Frank or KIF in which case I need to find a way to boot onto the device.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
