<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: cocoaheads | Stewart Gleadow's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.stewgleadow.com/blog/categories/cocoaheads/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.stewgleadow.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-07-02T15:09:55+10:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.stewgleadow.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Stewart Gleadow]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Xcode 4 Shortcuts Lightning Talk]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.stewgleadow.com/blog/2011/04/19/xcode-4-shortcuts-lightning-talk/"/>
    <updated>2011-04-19T16:46:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.stewgleadow.com/blog/2011/04/19/xcode-4-shortcuts-lightning-talk</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last week I have a short lightning talk with Jesse Collis (@sirjec) at the Melbourne Cocoaheads meetup. The topic was fairly boring, just some useful Xcode 4 shortcuts we have found since switching from Xcode 3 a few weeks ago. It ended up being a bit of a laugh, probably the first and only time a talk about keyboard shortcuts will be funny - I think it had something to do with the pizza and beer that had just arrived.</p>

<p>Jesse saved me the effort of writing up anything more and linking to the slides on his blog below.</p>

<p><a href="http://blog.jcmultimedia.com.au/2011/04/xcode4-shortcuts-melbourne-cocoaheads-april-2011.html">http://blog.jcmultimedia.com.au/2011/04/xcode4-shortcuts-melbourne-cocoaheads-april-2011.html</a></p>

<p>I've managed to find the <a href="http://vimeo.com/22598371">video footage of the xcode shortcuts talk</a> put together by Oliver Jones (@orj) on vimeo. After flicking through the footage a couple of questions were raised that I can now answer:</p>

<ul>
<li>Q: <em>Does Cmd+Option+[ or ] work if multiple lines are selected?</em><br/>
A: Yes.</li>
<li>Q: <em>Does Ctrl+6 for the class outline in the jump bar work in non-primary editors?</em><br/>
A: Yes, it is based on the editor that has focus.</li>
<li>Follow up: <em>Proper clean (Cmd+Option+Shift+K) did not completely clean the build for us.</em><br/>
<code>rm -rf</code> is still your friend</li>
</ul>


<p>The Melbourne Cocoaheads faithful also contributed some keyboard shortcuts of their own, here are the ones I jotted down:</p>

<ul>
<li><em>Cmd+Ctrl+Opt+?</em> - open item under the cursor in Xcode help ("real help, not the stupid little help" @tupps)</li>
<li><em>Cmd+Double-Click</em> - drill through to the implementation</li>
<li><em>Cmd+Opt+,</em> - open current file back in the main editor</li>
<li><em>Cmd+/</em> - Comment Line</li>
<li><em>Cmd+Shift+[ or ]</em> - navigate back and forth between tabs</li>
<li><em>Cmd+T</em> - Open new tab (same as Safari)</li>
<li><em>Cmd+Ctrl+Up and Down</em> - switch between counterparts</li>
</ul>


<p>and a few more shortcuts I've found since then:</p>

<ul>
<li><em>Cmd+Ctrl+Opt+Up</em> - open up the counterpart in the secondary editor</li>
<li><em>...</em> - Organise Import... just kidding. Maybe one day.</li>
</ul>


<p>I'm sure there are plenty more shortcuts I haven't found yet. Let me know the ones you find most useful.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
